let's look at the solution to this
second part of this quiz which is about
figuring out when do these two
instructions issue dispatch and write
results we first have to figure out when
the adhere will issue
normally it would issue in cycle five
assuming that the reservation station is
available let's check whether a
reservation station is available in
cycle five at this time we have already
issued two ads so we have occupied both
of the reservation stations so one is
available here only if one of these two
ads free is a reservation station before
a cycle five so reservation station is
available only if one of these two frees
its reservation station before cycle
five note that a reservation station is
to be freed a cycle earlier than when we
allocated so if we are going to use it
in cycle five it needs to be freed in
cycle four unfortunately these two ads
do not release their reservation
stations until cycles 10 and 12 the
first one that becomes available will be
freed in cycle 10 it cannot be allocated
to this ad immediately so this ad can
only issue in cycle 11 because it needs
this reservation station once this ad
issues it might dispatch in cycle 12
assuming that it has no dependencies and
indeed it doesn't so it issues in cycle
12 and then executes for one cycle and
broadcasts its result in cycle 13 the
next ad here will issue in cycle 12
because issue needs to be done in order
so if this one issues in cycle 11 the
next ad in the program order will not be
considered for issuing until cycle 12 so
we will try it cycle 12 but we have to
check whether a reservation station is
available this ad by then has freed a
reservation station but these two are
still holding on to theirs know that
this ad here is freeing its reservation
station in cycle 12 but it cannot be
allocated to a new instruction in the
same cycle
so they said here actually issues in
cycle 13 and then it doesn't wait for
anything because f3 and f4 are not
produced by previous instructions so it
will dispatch in cycle 14 and finally
write its result in cycle 15